<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Chernobyl Tours</string>

    <string name="choose_language">Choose language</string>

    <string name="en_click_me">Click image to set English</string>
    <string name="sp_click_me">Cliquez sur l\'image pour définir l'espagnol</string>
    <string name="fr_click_me">Cliquez sur l\'image pour définir le français</string>
    <string name ="ja_click_me">日本語を設定する画像をクリック</string>
    <string name ="zh_click_me">“點擊我”>點擊圖片設置中文</string>


    <string name="navigation_drawer_open">Open navigation drawer</string>
    <string name="navigation_drawer_close">Close navigation drawer</string>

    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>

    <string name="facebook_app_id">299931483831093</string>
    <string name="fb_login_protocol_scheme" translatable="false">fb299931483831093</string>
    <string name="google_maps_key" templateMergeStrategy="preserve" translatable="false">
        AIzaSyAv6U6eH2WbidLdc81XZNKYc1LOKR1JqN0
    </string>


    <string name="first_time_here"><a href="https://www.tourkiev.com/">First time here?</a></string>
    <string name="loading">Loading</string>

    <string name="tour_starting_point">Tour Starting Point</string>
    <string name="kreschatic_street">Kreschatik Street</string>
    <string name="podol">Podol</string>
    <string name="novi_petrivtsi">Novi Petrivtsi</string>
    <string name="dymer">Dymer</string>
    <string name="katyuzhanka">Katyuzhanka</string>
    <string name="ivankiv">Ivankiv</string>
    <string name="dityatki_check_point">Dityatki Check Point</string>
    <string name="thirty_k_zone">30k zone</string>
    <string name="zalesye_village">Zalesye Village</string>
    <string name="chornobyl">Chornobyl</string>
    <string name="trumpeting_angel_of_chornobyl">Trumpeting Angel of Chernobyl</string>
    <string name="monuments_to_liquidator">Monuments to liquidator</string>
    <string name="robots">Robots</string>
    <string name="elijah_church">Elijah church</string>
    <string name="radar_duga">Radar Duga</string>
    <string name="kopachi_village">Kopachi Village</string>
    <string name="first_part_of_reactor">1st part Nuclear Power Plant</string>
    <string name="chernobyl_new_safe_confinement">Chernobyl New Safe Confinement</string>
    <string name="second_part_power_part">2nd part power plant</string>
    <string name="pripyat_town">Pripyat town</string>
    <string name="pripyat_river_point">Pripyat river point</string>
    <string name="centre">Centre</string>
    <string name="ferris_wheel">Ferris wheel</string>
    <string name="stadium_avangard">Stadium avangard</string>
    <string name="swimming_pool">Swimming pool</string>
    <string name="jupiter_factory">Jupiter factory</string>
    <string name="police_station">Police station</string>

    <string name="tour_starting_point_description">We start our journey from the down town of Kiev, capital of Ukraine.  Since 2000 SoloEast Travel vehicles would leave this meeting point on the Independence Square to the World\'s Most Unique Places To Visit - Chernobyl Exclusion Land.  It takes two hours to get to the check point to the zone. Usually we play a documentary you can watch now - which is in English. Or you can keep listening to our guide in your language.</string>
    <string name="kreshatik_street_description">Now we enter the main street in Kiev - Kreschatik street. Once the hunting ground for princes and nobleman, Kreschatik used to be known for its magnificent landscapes, lush valleys and sparkling rivers. Construction on the site began in the eighteenth century as dwellings began to take shape on the land, with historical buildings such as the Kiev Theater the first to be built in the city in 1805. By 1837 Kreschatik was considered to be one of the most modern streets in Ukraine, and has retained its popularity as a landmark of the city and a well-known tourist destination. As the street became paved and architectural wonders began to line the chestnut tree filled Kreschatik, it developed into a playground for the rich and famous. It is still synonymous with luxury, elegance and high fashion. During both World War I and World War II, the street came into the line of fire and was almost completely destroyed. Fortunately, reconstruction efforts were begun immediately after the war came to an end in 1943 and saw to it that the street became a little wider and buildings began to take higher forms. Kreschatik was also always ahead of the news, having newspapers from Moscow, Belgium and other countries and cities delivered to the shops and home owners living along the street. Its charm and refined street lights can still be viewed to today. Even though the historical buildings are still decorating the street, it has continued to be a trendy site as visitors will find the latest fashions and most exquisite restaurants situated here. Confectionaries, hotels and department stores provide the best Kiev has to offer, and is as popular with locals as it is with tourists. Other attractions on Kreschatik include the National Philharmonic, trade buildings, international banking institutions, the Stolipin Monument, the Alexander the Liberator Monument, Nezalezhnosti Square, European Square, Franko Theater and the Verkhovna Rada. Kreschatik is more than just an attraction or street lined with history and wonder. It is the pride of Kiev and a way of life to many. Visitors to Kiev are recommended to stroll down Kreschatik, where they will be able to experience the heritage of the city, as well as the style of the high society in Ukraine.</string>
    <string name="podol_description">We are entering famous Kiev\'s district called Podol.  It is one of the oldest neighborhoods of Kyiv, and the birthplace of the city\'s trade, commerce and industry. It contains many architectural and historical landmarks, and new archaeological sites are still being revealed.  The name “Podil” means something that is situated downwards. This area used to be the trading and crafting center of Kyiv. The names of some Podil neighborhoods reflect this fact: \"Dehtyari\" (those who works with tar), \"Honchari\" (potters), \"Kozhemyaki\" (craftsmen working with leather). On the territory of Podil were found ancient constructions, some of them date back to 9th–11th century. Intensive building within Podil took place in the 17th century. An annual fair was conducted since 1797.  Before the Great Podil fire of 1811 it was the most populous neighborhood of the city with 2,068 houses out of 3,672 dwellings in all of Kyiv. The fire damaged the neighborhood extensively and changed the appearance of Podil dramatically. After the fire Podil was newly planned and a large number of new streets appeared, which still exist today. At this time were constructed such buildings as Contract\'s House, the National University of Kyiv-Mohyla Academy, shopping arcade and others.  Until World War II, the section just north of Nyzhniy Val street was called Ploska chast or Ploskaya sloboda. It was home to many poor Jews who lived there in wretched conditions.</string>
    <string name="novi_petrivtsi_description">We are passing by Novi Petrivtsi, one of Ukrainian villages, which got popular for the territory of the former Mezhyhirya Monastery that in 2008-2009 was in the epicenter of a big political scandal.   The huge house and extensive grounds (including a Zoo!) was the former private residence of the 4th President of Ukraine Viktor Yanukovych The territory is enclosed by a five meter tall fence along the 54 km (34 mi) perimeter. On its territory are located a yacht pier, equestrian club, shooting range, tennis court and many other recreational tourism complexes as well as hunting grounds. Mezhyhirya required a staffing level of 2,000 people and daily maintenance costs of $75,000.  This unbelievable waste and political corruption ended in 2014 when Yanukovych was forced to resign during the Revolution of Dignity. Today the Mezhyhirya Residence is a modern day palace, and for visitors it is an interesting alternative day trip for longer holidays based in Kiev.</string>
    <string name="dymer_description">We are approaching to a village called Dymer. It was found in X-XI. Dymer\'s name came from the word \"дым\" which means smog in English. Because of many factories they had there was much of smog around the town. That\'s why it got such name. It used to be a Polish town until 1703. Then Semen Paliy crashed in and took over lordship over the territory. Dymer never was the same. It became a village with lot\'s of memories. Nevertheless Dymer is not the tiniest settlement in Ukraine.   Beyond all the factories it has, there are also a sewing factory, three gas stations, auto park, two schools, two libraries, centre of art, musical school and a hospital.</string>
    <string name="katyachanka_description">Now we are passing by an ancient village called Katyuzhanka. It was found in 1500s. It\'s name came from the first inhabitant Katyuga. Katyuzhanka gave us two very famous actresses - anchorweman Olga and Natalia Sumska.  There is also one more interesting thing it is famous for. About 500 people come here each weekends to get healed from smoking, drinking alcohol etc. Orthodox priest Olexander listens to everyone\'s needs in turns and explains that they\'ll be badly punished by God if they smoke or drink alcohol during the year. If someone can\'t live without at least one cigarette a day, they will be allowed to take some. But not more than they would agree with the priest.</string>
    <string name="ivankiv_description">Here we are in Ivankiv where we can see an interesting monument. So called \"Egg of Life\". Sculpture quite unusual, and this attracts the attention of tourists. \"Egg life\" was established in 2000. This concrete work of art was donated to the village by the German architect A. Kolbe. The monument is a symbol of rebirth and fertility life I land affected after the Chernobyl tragedy.   In the middle of the 15th century the territory around modern Ivankiv was called Zemlya Trudinivska (Trudinivska Land). It was a property of Kiev boyar Olehnja Juhnovich. In 1524 King of Poland Sigismund I the Old gave this land to Kiev Burgess Tishko Proskura. In 1589 Ivan Proskura became the owner of this land. The town was founded in 1589 and named after Ivan Proskura. At first it was called Ivaniv and Ivanivka, which were later changed to Ivankiv. At the beginning of the 17th century Crimean Tatars made four military campaigns on Polesia and as a result many people in Ivankiv were killed, taken prisoner and sold into slavery. The town is located 42 miles south from the Chernobyl power plant, with the entrance to the exclusion zone being located 20 miles north. The town was not as affected by the Chernobyl disaster compared to other towns. Ivankiv raion has increased in 1986 after the disestablishment of the Chernobyl Raion due to the Chernobyl disaster. Today Ivankiv Raion administers the former territory of the depopulated region that is majorly part of the zone of alienation and supervised by the Ministry of Emergencies of Ukraine.</string>
    <string name="dityatki_check_point_description">We are approaching to the first checkpoint on our way. Please, don\'t take pictures of it and the personal of checkpoint as well. As it can cause a trouble for the group. But you are welcome to take pictures of the posters close to it. During the day there will be couple more check points which we are not to take pictures of.  Here we are at the main entrance to the exclusion zone. This is so cold Dytyatki checkpoint. The name comes from the village nearby Dytyatky.  This is one of the few villages outside Chernobyl exclusion zone that belong to Chernobyl district before the accident. Most of the villages where evacuated. There are only 1000 inhabitants in Dytyaky - many unemployed. Since the place belongs to the category four (places that suffered from radiation the most) - Ukrainian government still runs here a welfare program, which helps people to survive. On the other hand according to the health care administration of the district - Dytyatky is recognized as the most depressive settlements in the area with extremely high level of alcohol addiction. The checkpoint was built here in 1986. Then main task of this Post is to eliminate the escape of radioactively contaminated articles from the Exclusion zone. Another very important Mission of this check point is a dosimeter Control of every person who leaves they area. Every visitor is obliged to pass through a special machine that will perform a complete radioactive contamination check and set an alarm if one is discovered. This Chernobyl guide is created by SoloEast Travel and aims only for it\'s customers.</string>
    <string name="thirty_k_zone_description">Welcome to The Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant Zone of Alienation.It is also commonly known as the Chernobyl Exclusion Zone, the 30 Kilometre Zone.Established by the USSR military soon after the 1986 disaster, it initially existed as an area of 30 km radius from the Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant designated for evacuation and placed under military control. The Exclusion Zone covers an area of approximately 2,600 km2 (1,000 sq mi) The Exclusion Zone\'s purpose is to restrict access to hazardous areas, reduce the spread of radiological contamination and conduct radiological and ecological monitoring activities. The 30 km Zone was initially divided into three subzones: the area immediately adjacent to Reactor 4, an area of approximately 10 km radius from the reactor and the remaining 30 km zone. Protective clothing and available facilities varied between these sub zones. You might think that radiation level jumps up here. But it\'s even lower than in Kiev. New roads were laid here so our car can safely move on right to the reactors. But if you walk further in the fields you may find many hot spots. Nevertheless some people came back to live here. We call them samosely (self-settlers). Mostly they are retired people who used to live here before the accident. There are 162 self-settlers who don\'t believe in any radiation because no one can taste, see or smell it. They live quite interesting and long life though everyone thought they would die soon. No coke, no fast-food, no long queues at banks))) These people have some chickens for meat, cats and dogs to spend time with. Also you may wonder of mutant animals, but we are not to see them here. They only lived several weeks or months after the accident and then died.Without people hunting animals and traffics in the streets nowadays Chernobyl exclusion zone became a paradise for wild nature. Here you can find 100 wolves. Two more hundred of them live in Belarus. Belorussian exclusion zone is completely abandoned that\'s why there are many more wild animals. Here in 30k zone you may also find raccoon dogs,beavers, polecats, red foxes, bisons, boars, moose, dears, badgers and Przewalski\'s horses. So entering the exclusion zone remember we are not alone here)</string>
    <string name="zalesye_village_description">Hardly you can say that we are in the village now. The Power Plant is 19 km away from us.Trees are everywhere and houses can be barely seen. Anyway, Zalesye was the biggest village in this area. About 3000 people lived here. They had a school, library, maternity hospital and so called in Soviet Union \"palace of culture\" where people gathered to for different reasons like watching movies or dancing, election etc. Now it\'s all gone. The village name itself sounds ironically as it means \"village behind the forest\"...The last self settler Rosaliya passed away in 2015. She was a teacher at local school. Rosaliya spent her last years without electricity and gas to heat the house and cook. Nevertheless she never complained.</string>
    <string name="chornobyl_description">Entering Chernobyl town one must know that the Power Plant is not situated right here. It’s 15 km away. Though Pripyat town is closer it was found only in 1970 specifically for the workers. And Chernobyl was the closest administrative center at that time.  Prior to the 20th century, Chernobyl was inhabited by Ukrainian and some Polish peasants, and a relatively large number of Jewish people. Later the town was chosen as the site of the first nuclear power station on Ukrainian soil. On 26 April 1986, Reactor No. 4 at the Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant melted down.  Chernobyl city was evacuated soon after the disaster. The base of operations for the administration and monitoring of the Chernobyl Exclusion Zone was moved from Pripyat to Chernobyl. Chernobyl currently contains offices for the State Agency of Ukraine on the Exclusion Zone Management and accommodation for visitors. 25% of Chernobyl town is in use. All in all here are 2000 of workers. There is a hospital for them to get a medical check, which they have 1-2 a year. A bus comes to Chernobyl three times a day. So it\'s not a big deal to get here. Also there is a gas station for govermental vehicles and one fire station. Blocks have been re-purposed as accommodation for employees of the State Agency. Because of regulations implemented to limit exposure, workers in the Chernobyl Exclusion Zone are limited in the number of days per week or weeks per month they stay in Chernobyl. Many types of animals live there now and the city has become overgrown.Chernobyl is not a happy place, while alcohol is plentiful there is little laughter, few women and no children.</string>
    <string name="trumpeting_angel_of_chornobyl_description">And the third angel sounded, and there fell a great star from heaven, burning as it were a lamp, and it fell upon the third part of the rivers, and upon the fountains of waters; And the name of the star is called Wormwood: and the third part of the waters became wormwood; and many men died of the waters, because they were made bitter. (Revelation 8:10-11)  Chernobyl is the Ukrainian word for “wormwood” and thus some believe that the Bible actually predicted the disaster at the power plant and subsequent contamination.  In front of you is a little elevated platform made of two layers. Its a map of the exclusion zone. Little spots on it represent the settlements which had to be evacuated. A bit farther you see the cross shaped signs, those are the names of the settlements.</string>
    <string name="monuments_to_liquidator_description">Located in front of the fire station is a memorial to the liquidators who rushed to reactor number four in the immediate aftermath of the explosion. The firefighters who initially responded to the disaster were unaware of the scale of the incident and while they labored to extinguish the fires, their bodies absorbed high doses of radiation, and many of them later died of Acute Radiation Sickness. Overall, an estimated 600,000 – 1 million workers, including scientists, miners, and Soviet military conscripts, participated in the Chernobyl cleanup efforts.  The plaque on the monument is inscribed “To those who saved the world.”</string>
    <string name="robots_description">During the Chernobyl disaster in 1986, Soviet authorities tried to spare human workers from the harsh conditions by experimenting with a number of bizarre and oddly innovative remote-controlled devices. These robotic machines are now on display at an open air museum near the site.  Just looking at these clunky old things you can immediately tell that they weren\'t up to the task. Removing the contaminated debris required more skill than these devices could offer, forcing the Soviets to send in workers (i.e. soldiers) to do the job. During the clean-up, each person could only afford to spend a maximum of 40 seconds inside or near the facility. Many of them died as a consequence of the exposure or later contracted cancer.  Anyway these robots were some help too. They were used at the spots where radiation reached 1000 Sieverts.</string>
    <string name="elijah_church_description">Over the entire twenty-five years since the Chernobyl nuclear plant accident, radiation levels in the area of St. Elijah Church, the only church operating in the exclusion zone, was well below levels across the zone, Chernobyl disaster liquidators state. \"Even during the most difficult days of 1986, the area around the St. Elijah Church was clean (from radiation - IF), not to mention that the church itself was also clean,\" president of the Ukrainian Chernobyl Union Yury Andreyev said in a Kiev-Moscow video conference on Wednesday.  Now, the territory adjacent to the church has a background level of 6 microroentgen per hour compared with 18 in Kiev.In particular, according to him, a few seconds after the explosion in the fourth unit of the Chernobyl PP the cloud containing uranium particles started moving in the direction of Pripyat, a city located about 1,800 meters from the plant. There was a pine-tree on its way (it is featured on a well-known icon Chernobyl\'s Savior.)  \"The cloud stopped short of this pine, divided into two parts by some unknown reason and continued moving to the left and right sides of the city instead of covering its residential areas. The radiation level in contamination areas was four or five roentgen per hour, and the city showed only half a milliroentgen,\" Andreyev said.</string>
    <string name="radar_duga_description">The secret military town Chernobyl-2 is located northwest of the small town of Chernobyl, but it is impossible to find on any topographical map. Exploring the maps, you are likely to find a symbol for a children’s boarding house, or a dotted line of forest roads on a place of accommodation of the town, but no reference to urban and technical buildings. In the USSR, they were able to hide a secret, even more so if it was a military secret. Only due to the collapse of the Soviet Union and the accident at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant did it become known of the existence of a small town (military garrison) in the Polissia woods which was engaged … in “space espionage.” In the seventies of the last century were created unique military radar systems to track ballistic missile launches from the territories (or military bases and submarines) of the likely opponent. The created radar system was named “Over-the-horizon radar station” (Duga-1) . The antenna was 150 meters tall and 500 meters wide, and this masterpiece of mechanical engineering weighs about 14,000 tons. Its enormous size and receiving antenna masts, Duga-1 demanded a large human resource – approximately 1,000 people worked on the military alert status at the site. The Duga systems were extremely powerful, over 10 MW in some cases, and broadcast in the shortwave radio bands. They appeared without warning, sounding like a sharp, repetitive tapping noise at 10 Hz, which led to it being nicknamed by shortwave listeners the Russian Woodpecker. The random frequency hops disrupted legitimate broadcast, amateur radio, commercial aviation communications, utility transmissions, and resulted in thousands of complaints by many countries worldwide. The signal became such a nuisance that some receivers such as amateur radios and televisions actually began including ‘Woodpecker Blankers’ in their design. The unclaimed signal was a source for much speculation, giving rise to theories such as Soviet mind control and weather control experiments. However, many experts and amateur radio hobbyists quickly realized it to be an over-the-horizon radar system. NATO military intelligence had already photographed the system and given it the NATO reporting name Steel Yard. This theory was publicly confirmed after the fall of the Soviet Union.When the Soviet Union fell apart in 1991, Ukraine and Russia began to talk about control over the numerous active Soviet military facilities in the Ukraine. The western Russian Woodpecker facility was not included in the talks, and what had been suspected in the larger world for some time was confirmed: the radar station had been too close to Chernobyl power plant.  When its Reactor #4 melted down, the Woodpecker was heavily contaminated by fallout, and had to be abandoned. Chernobyl-2 was evacuated, and the station’s movable equipment was shipped off to the other Woodpecker in Siberia. The main antenna array was far too massive to ship out, so it stayed behind and (doubly isolated by state secrecy and nuclear radiation) even provoked rumors that it had somehow caused the meltdown.</string>
    <string name="kopachi_village_description">Before you step out of the car remember that our rout is safe though there several hot spots you\'ll see. They are not dangerous for you to be next to it. Just don\'t put anything to the ground! Your geiger shows level of radiation per hour. During the day we get 2,2mk Sieverts which people get simply staying at home for 24 hours.  Nothing has changed much behind the window. The trees are everywhere just like a minute ride before. We are in the village called Kopachi. After the Chernobyl disaster in 1986 the village was highly contaminated by fallout and subsequently evacuated. After Kopachi village was evacuated by the authorities, all the houses were torn down and buried, as an experiment. This village was the only village suffering this fate as a result of the Chernobyl disaster.  A kindergarten and one other brick building are the only architectural structures that remain standing, all other buildings were bulldozed. The government did not recognize the fact that these highly-contaminated buildings and houses would seep radioactive isotopes into the water table. Burying the buildings drove radio-toxins deeper into the environment. The soil and water surrounding the former village remain contaminated with radioactive materials including plutonium, strontium-90, and caesium-137. Other villages in the exclusion zone faced a similar fate, thus polluting the aquifer</string>
    <string name="first_part_of_reactor_description">The V.I. Lenin Nuclear Power Station as it was known during the Soviet times, consisted of four reactors of type RBMK-1000, each capable of producing 1,000 megawatts (MW) of electric power. They were also working on the reactors #5-6. Reactor #5 was 85% ready when the accident happened. Entering the territory of Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant you can see two cooling towers on the right. They were planned for the last two reactors. You can find them on the right side from the bus. They are two red buildings surrounded by cranes which were left the way they were standing at the accident time. Cooling canal right next to them was used for the first 4 reactors. On the left side is a new storage for the nuclear wastes and the concrete plant next to it is only used for the needs of exclusion zone. The huge structure in front of us is the sarcophagus which is going to cover the 4th reactor for next 100 years. You\'ve probably noticed already two huge black buildings on the right which look more like boxes. From right to left that\'s reactor #1 and two next to the ventilation tube. If you look to the left side from it you can see two rusty buildings. The bigger one is reactor #3 and reactor number 4 is just a bit smaller, stands next to the ventilation tube. It is difficult to imagine, but after the disaster Chernobyl Power Plant produced more power than before. Because the 3d reactor continued working up to 2000.  Now we make a short stop for panoramic pictures with all reactors in it. Please, don’t go behind the fence or anywhere far from the tour bus.</string>
    <string name="chernobyl_new_safe_confinement_description">As we get closer to the reactors remember please that we are not to take pictures of personal and the right side from the sarcophagus. As for the reactors, the sarcophagus and the monument you are more then welcome to take pictures of them. Also please, don\'t cross the road behind the monument which you are going to see in a second. Chernobyl’s New Safe Confinement is a design and construction project unprecedented in the history of engineering. Never before has such a huge structure been constructed at a heavily contaminated site. The structure was moved 327 metres from its assembly point to its final resting place in November 2016.  The New Safe Confinement will prevent the release of contaminated material from the present shelter and at the same time protect the structure from external impacts such as extreme weather.  The structure is 108 metres high and 162 metres long, and has a span of 257 metres and a lifetime of a minimum of 100 years. it is tall enough to house London’s St Paul’s or Paris’ Notre Dame cathedrals.   The arch-shaped structure weighs some 36,000 tonnes. Its frame is a huge lattice construction of tubular steel members, supported by two longitudinal concrete beams. It is strong enough to withstand a tornado and its sophisticated ventilation system eliminates the risk of corrosion, ensuring that there is no need to replace the coating and expose workers to radiation during the structure’s lifetime. The consortium worked with local sub-contractors and others from across the world. For instance, the arch was made of structural elements designed and built in Italy. The cranes were manufactured in the US. The arch cladding contractor was from Turkey, and lifting and sliding operations were carried out by a Dutch company.</string>
    <string name="second_part_power_plant">On April 26, 1986, during a test to see how much power was needed to keep the reactor No. 4 reactor operating in the event of a blackout, the Chernobyl Nuclear Station exploded, releasing extremely dangerous amounts of radioactive chemicals into the air, which over time contaminated millions of square miles in dozens of European nations.Thirty one deaths are directly attributed to the accident, all among the reactor staff and emergency workers.   It is difficult to judge now what is the exact number of people who died after getting a dose, as people die and fall ill everyday even without radiation. In 2006 The World Health organisation predicted 30,000 to 60,000 cancer deaths as a result of Chernobyl fallout. The scientists talk about different health problems as a result of this tragedy. Cancer is probably what comes to our mind first. But people who didn\'t suffer directly from radiation had another challenge. They were stressed by evacuation, loosing their homes, jobs, all the social problems it caused and a fear of radiation of course. Chernobyl accident directly took 29 lives of liquidators.</string>
    <string name="pripyat_town_descriptuion">Found in winter 1970 Pripyat town was a peaceful place. At the moment of accident there were 50.000 people. 1000 babies were born each year. Average age of inhabitants was 26-27years.16 weddings were organised on that tragedy day. On the evening April 26 town was still alive. People were walking in the streets enjoying their time. If someone felt that something was wrong, they couldn\'t even imagine how bad the situation was. The next evening Pripyat sank in silence. This silence has been holding town in its arms for many years. And still not going to let it live again. Though Soviet Union was full of secrets, Chernobyl disaster is something much bigger than Soviet Union could hide. They had to evacuate people. To avoid panic government sent policemen to every apartment to tell people there were busses waiting for them at 2pm. A radio would also inform people briefly of what was happening. Some people really believed that they would return in couple days as they were told. Taking into account that they only had to take the most important belongings like documents. But they never made it back. After 1300 buses sent from Kiev evacuated people, they only were let in half a year after disaster. Just to take some more stuff from their homes. But it was not the same home anymore.</string>
    <string name="pripyat_river_point_description">River port was favourite place for all Pripyat inhabitants. Neither fans nor air-conditioning were popular at that time. light breeze was coming from Pripyat river, nice view from caffe also called Pripyat. They say ice-cream tasted good there. Wendy machines with one cup for everybody. True comrades these people were. Only a \"black sheep\" of family would bring own cup from home.  Though it would take double price and more time to get to Kiev by ship than by buss, the river port was overcrowded always. The boat you can see on the right side coming close to the river is a floating dock. The ships were making their turn here and go back to Kiev. The waves were too high to let people straight to the bank. From Pripyat river port people could also go to Gomel, Belarus. Also here was the first in Soviet Union yacht club. Pripyat river is connected with cooling canal for the first 4 reactors, then with Dnepr which is connected with Black sea. Another interesting fact about Pripyat river is that 80% of it\'s contamination it gets outside of the exclusion sone. It is known that Belarus got more radiation than Ukraine. \"As you sow, so shall you reap\" they say... When you walk up stairs from the river port pay attention to the left side. There you\'ll find a hot spot. After the explosion cars which took part in the clean up had to be washed. Water was streaming down the stairs. Radiation does\'t care much about how much time passes.</string>
    <string name="centre_description">It\'s difficult to imagine now that kids were playing all around. Pripyat was a beautiful town with more than 30.000 bushes of roses. You won\'t find any ancient structure here. As Pripyat was completely new. It only existed 16 years. You are in centre of town now. Go ahead and see one of the first supermarkets in Soviet Union. It will be on the left side once you walk up the stairs. It\'s connected with a restaurant. If you look at the walls carefully, you can see pictures left here by artists.  Hotel Polesie on the right hand. After evacuation they tried to run town again, to put new asphalt roads, to clean buildings with special aqua. But they realised it was not to be done. Anyway it was in use till 1997. The workers of Power Plant, the liquidators and some governmental representatives stayed here. They put plastic cover in some of the buildings (like swimming pool, hotel). So it prevented absorption of radiation. If you look in front you see Cultural - entertainment centre or so called Palace of culture. Pripyat inhabitants were active people. They organised lots of activities here. Theatre, cinema, gym, a pool for kids all this in one building. Also here were radio amateurs and literature clubs. Come closer to our Palace of culture and the first thing you see opening the door is propaganda room. Please don\'t walk far inside because the floor is very poor there! You may walk to the first room and take as many pictures as you like. You can even find a voting box here. Only communist party they had...But voting existed...</string>
    <string name="ferris_wheel_description">For nearly 30 years, the Pripyat Amusement Park has stood empty and alone. The rides were hardly enjoyed. The giant Ferris wheel was never loaded. The park was only opened for one day, and almost immediately abandoned. It’s been this way ever since, and it’s still very much haunted by the ghosts of its past. Park was going to open on May 1, 1986 but opening day never arrived.Tragedy happened on the 26 of April. The reactor had blown, but the town wasn\'t told of the disaster right away. While children played outside, plumes of smoke were slowly drifting in the Pripyat’s direction. A fleet of buses arrived the next day for forced evacuations.The park was opened, briefly, on April 27, 1986, a few days ahead of schedule. However, it was not operating for the sake of financial gain. The owners opened it up for a few hours while the town was being evacuated, in an attempt to lessen some of the tragedy and terrible feelings of the day.Now the ferris wheels rusts away next to a small and simple merry-go-round, a boat swing and a bumper car – hard to imagine that this small collection of rides was once considered an attraction for 50,000 people… While the concrete parts are mostly safe nowadays, the surrounding moss can be as high as 20 µSv/h (microsievert per hour) – the radioactive particles were simply washed into the soil. Walking across such a spot like that won’t harm you instantly, but you don’t wanna build a house there as it is about 400 times the normal terrestrial radiation…</string>
    <string name="stadium_avangard_description">Hardly you can imagine some teams playing football around. But what you see is a soccer field.The stadium was built in the year of the disaster. It should’ve opened May 1, 1986. Soccer was incredibly popular in Pripyat – each reactor had its own team.The field was used a couple of times, but the official opening never took place. Today the field is overgrown and the grandstand is crumbling down. It\'s turbine was made for 5000 people.</string>
    <string name="swimming_pool_description">Now we are going to the swimming pool. No water you\'ll find there today.  It was built in the 1970s and was used until 1998 (12 years after the Chernobyl disaster); during those 12 years the swimming pool was mainly used by the liquidators. The swimming pool is considered one of the cleanest places of Pripyat.</string>
    <string name="jupiter_factory_description">Now we come to one very important object in town. The Jupiter Factory. As many university-educated people lived in Pripyat, the Soviet Union decided to build a factory in the outskirts to employ part of that people. This factory became the second employer in the area after the Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant. The factory opened in 1980 and employed around 3500 people.  The \"Jupiter\" factory of Pripyat is a legend. According to the official history they used to make cassette recorders and other minor parts, but most of its shops made very different products. Secretly, in the grounds of \"Jupiter\" they were developing and assembling military computers and \"black boxes\", those products were mysteriously named \"Product No:\". Even today it is still not known for sure what products came off the assembly line here. We can only say that most of them were used for military submarines, fighters and even in the space industry.  After the Chernobyl disaster in 1986, unlike Pripyat, the factory wasn\'t permanently abandoned. After some time, part of the employees return to Jupiter and the factory became a radiological laboratory for testing of various decontamination techniques and developing dosimetric instruments. The factory was operating until 1996.</string>
    <string name="police_station_description">Although Pripyat was a city predominantly inhabited by educated and privileged people of course no city of that size could exist without a police station – it sounds so cliché, but most of the arrested people were accused of alcohol related deeds: making home-brew liquor (samogon, самого́н), rarely driving under influence or being drunk in public. The crime rate was next to nothing in Pripyat.</string>
    <string name="nearest_point">Nearest point is :</string>
    <string name="start">Start</string>
    <string name="title_activity_settings">Settings</string>

    <!-- Strings related to Settings -->

    <!-- Example General settings -->
    <string name="pref_header_general">General</string>

    <string name="pref_title_social_recommendations">Enable social recommendations</string>
    <string name="pref_description_social_recommendations">Recommendations for people to contact
        based on your message history
    </string>

    <string name="pref_title_display_name">Display name</string>
    <string name="pref_default_display_name">John Smith</string>

    <string name="pref_title_add_friends_to_messages">Add friends to messages</string>
    <string-array name="pref_example_list_titles">
        <item>Always</item>
        <item>When possible</item>
        <item>Never</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="pref_example_list_values">
        <item>1</item>
        <item>0</item>
        <item>-1</item>
    </string-array>

    <!-- Example settings for Data & Sync -->
    <string name="pref_header_data_sync">Data &amp; sync</string>

    <string name="pref_title_sync_frequency">Sync frequency</string>
    <string-array name="pref_sync_frequency_titles">
        <item>15 minutes</item>
        <item>30 minutes</item>
        <item>1 hour</item>
        <item>3 hours</item>
        <item>6 hours</item>
        <item>Never</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="pref_sync_frequency_values">
        <item>15</item>
        <item>30</item>
        <item>60</item>
        <item>180</item>
        <item>360</item>
        <item>-1</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="list_preference_entries">
        <item>Entry 1</item>
        <item>Entry 2</item>
        <item>Entry 3</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="list_preference_entry_values">
        <item>1</item>
        <item>2</item>
        <item>3</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="multi_select_list_preference_default_value" />

    <string name="pref_title_system_sync_settings">System sync settings</string>

    <!-- Example settings for Notifications -->
    <string name="pref_header_notifications">Notifications</string>

    <string name="pref_title_new_message_notifications">New message notifications</string>

    <string name="pref_title_ringtone">Ringtone</string>
    <string name="pref_ringtone_silent">Silent</string>

    <string name="pref_title_vibrate">Vibrate</string>
    <string name="log_out">Log out</string>
    <string name="about_us">About us</string>
    <string name="language">Language</string>
    <string name="book_a_tour">Book a tour</string>
    <string name="map">Map</string>
    <string name="greetings">Greetings</string>

</resources>
